<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<component type="desktop-application">
  <id>io.github.mmhfarooque.GuiSpeedTest</id>
  <launchable type="desktop-id">io.github.mmhfarooque.GuiSpeedTest.desktop</launchable>
  <name>GUI Speed Test for Linux</name>
  <summary>Multi-backend internet speed test</summary>
  <description>
    <p>
      Fast, no-nonsense internet speed test with a native GTK4 + libadwaita
      interface that follows your system light/dark theme.
    </p>
    <p>Four backends behind one picker so you can run the test against whichever server you trust most:</p>
    <ul>
      <li>Cloudflare — global anycast, hits the nearest PoP (default)</li>
      <li>Ookla Speedtest — wraps the official Ookla CLI</li>
      <li>M-Lab NDT7 — academic/research-backed, non-commercial</li>
      <li>LibreSpeed — open-source, configurable self-hosted server</li>
    </ul>
    <p>
      Command-line and JSON output modes are also available for
      scripting and logging.
    </p>
  </description>
  <url type="homepage">https://github.com/mmhfarooque/gui-speedtest</url>
  <url type="bugtracker">https://github.com/mmhfarooque/gui-speedtest/issues</url>
  <url type="vcs-browser">https://github.com/mmhfarooque/gui-speedtest</url>
  <developer id="io.github.mmhfarooque">
    <name>Mahmud Farooque</name>
  </developer>
  <metadata_license>CC0-1.0</metadata_license>
  <project_license>GPL-3.0-or-later</project_license>
  <categories>
    <category>Network</category>
    <category>Utility</category>
  </categories>
  <keywords>
    <keyword>speedtest</keyword>
    <keyword>bandwidth</keyword>
    <keyword>internet</keyword>
    <keyword>network</keyword>
    <keyword>cloudflare</keyword>
    <keyword>ookla</keyword>
  </keywords>
  <content_rating type="oars-1.1"/>
  <releases>
    <release version="1.6.10" date="2026-04-19">
      <description>
        <p>AppImage build-script fix — dynamic lookup of the latest available python3.12.x starter tag.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="1.6.9" date="2026-04-19">
      <description>
        <p>AppImage build-script fix — use curl to fetch the prebuilt CPython AppImage directly instead of the python-appimage CLI.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="1.6.8" date="2026-04-19">
      <description>
        <p>Packaging parity push — Flatpak now bundles websocket-client so M-Lab works. RPM, AppImage, and Snap build scripts fixed. Goal is feature parity across all formats (all four backends available).</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="1.6.7" date="2026-04-19">
      <description>
        <p>RPM workflow fix — tar-based tarball prep replaces git archive for the Fedora container build.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="1.6.6" date="2026-04-19">
      <description>
        <p>Release workflow fix — wait for all format jobs before creating the GitHub Release (previous run raced past Flatpak).</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="1.6.5" date="2026-04-19">
      <description>
        <p>Release workflow fix — attach the Flatpak bundle to the GitHub Release (previous run built it but the file glob missed the action's output path).</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="1.6.4" date="2026-04-19">
      <description>
        <p>Flatpak build-chain fix — revert runtime to GNOME 47 (gnome-48 CI image not yet published).</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="1.6.3" date="2026-04-19">
      <description>
        <p>Flatpak workflow fix — runtime bumped to GNOME 48 (47 was EOL). Same app code as 1.6.0.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="1.6.2" date="2026-04-19">
      <description>
        <p>Workflow-only fix — corrects the Flatpak container image name. Same code as 1.6.1/1.6.0.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="1.6.1" date="2026-04-19">
      <description>
        <p>Packaging-only release — first build to include AppImage, Snap, Flatpak, and RPM alongside the existing .deb, wheel, and sdist. Same code as 1.6.0.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="1.6.0" date="2026-04-19">
      <description>
        <p>Ookla backend: live-progress rewrite. Sparklines, ping bars, and speed numbers now animate in real time during an Ookla run instead of sitting silent until the end. Run Again now triggers a fresh speedtest (previously re-used the cached result). Error messages from backend failures wrap inside the card instead of pushing the window wider. Ookla install helper now forces IPv4 and adds hard timeouts so it can't hang on broken IPv6 transit.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="1.5.3" date="2026-04-19">
      <description>
        <p>Hotfix for networks with broken IPv6 transit — connection_info and the HTTP-based backends now prefer IPv4. Observed 40-100x speedup on affected paths; no change for working networks.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="1.5.2" date="2026-04-19">
      <description>
        <p>Hotfix: unbreak .deb install on Ubuntu 26.04 — the transitional policykit-1 package was removed, so the dependency is now polkitd | policykit-1.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="1.5.1" date="2026-04-19">
      <description>
        <p>Ookla backend can now be enabled directly from the GUI — click the "Install" button on the "Enable Ookla" row, enter your password at the polkit prompt, and the backend picker refreshes. No terminal required.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="1.5.0" date="2026-04-19">
      <description>
        <p>New helper: sudo gui-speedtest-install-ookla installs Ookla's official CLI automatically, with distro detection for Ubuntu 26.04 (falls back to tarball when the apt repo doesn't yet support your release). Also: actionable hints in the log for every missing backend.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="1.4.0" date="2026-04-19">
      <description>
        <p>OVH backend removed — it was geography-bound to Europe/North America and didn't give useful numbers for other regions. Four backends remain: Cloudflare (default), Ookla, M-Lab NDT7, LibreSpeed.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="1.3.2" date="2026-04-19">
      <description>
        <p>Cancel now gives instant UI feedback instead of staying on the old "Testing…" text for seconds. New "Clear" button in the log viewer wipes the log for a clean trace on the next run.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="1.3.1" date="2026-04-19">
      <description>
        <p>Fixes the sparklines and ping histogram not rendering on Ubuntu 26.04 — the charts now draw correctly. Root cause was a missing python3-gi-cairo glue package; it's now a hard dep.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="1.3.0" date="2026-04-18">
      <description>
        <p>Live sparkline charts inside the download and upload cards show throughput history in real time. Ping card shows a bar histogram — one bar per latency sample so jitter and outliers are visible at a glance. Cairo-drawn, no new dependencies.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="1.2.3" date="2026-04-18">
      <description>
        <p>Download/upload cards now update continuously during each chunk. Slow chunks (under 1 Mbps) no longer make the app look frozen.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="1.2.2" date="2026-04-18">
      <description>
        <p>New "Log" button in the header bar opens an in-app log viewer with Copy All — no terminal needed to read or share the log.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="1.2.1" date="2026-04-18">
      <description>
        <p>Persistent file logging at ~/.cache/gui-speedtest/gui-speedtest.log — rotating, always on. Per-chunk timings, phase transitions, cancel events recorded for diagnosis.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="1.2.0" date="2026-04-18">
      <description>
        <p>Measurement accuracy: bigger Cloudflare upload chunks for correct saturation, OVH auto-picks nearest mirror (Gravelines or Beauharnois), M-Lab upload uses server-reported byte counts.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="1.1.3" date="2026-04-18">
      <description>
        <p>Fixes the "Is Not Responding" freeze when Cancel was clicked on a slow OVH download — now uses socket.shutdown() instead of resp.close() (thread-safe, non-blocking) and checks a cancellation flag between chunks.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="1.1.2" date="2026-04-18">
      <description>
        <p>Larger default window so the full control set fits on first open without dragging. Minimum size pinned to keep the layout sane if resized.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="1.1.1" date="2026-04-18">
      <description>
        <p>Cancel button now aborts in-flight HTTP downloads and M-Lab WebSocket streams immediately instead of waiting for the current chunk to finish.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="1.1.0" date="2026-04-18">
      <description>
        <p>Ookla binary identity check, real M-Lab latency measurement, M-Lab client IP/ISP enrichment, in-test Cancel button, AppStream metainfo, AppImage support.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="1.0.1" date="2026-04-18">
      <description>
        <p>Security: websocket-client CVE-2024-5569 closed; M-Lab frame size cap. Packaging: 3.0 quilt source format, GTK 4.12 pin, find-based package discovery. CI: Node 24 action bumps, Python 3.10-3.13 matrix.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="1.0.0" date="2026-04-18">
      <description>
        <p>Initial release.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
  </releases>
</component>
